Guide to the Cuban Revolution Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Andrew St. George Photographs, Films, and Papers, 1957-1960; Series I
  - Photographs
    - Contact Book IV
      - Book IV Print 78: Fidel Castro on "Meet the Press"; Fidel Castro at National Press Club luncheon, 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 324)
        Top frames show Fidel Castro in a televised appearance on the NBC news show "Meet the Press." All other frames depict Fidel as he addressed attendants at a luncheon held by the National Press Club in Washington, D.C., in mid-April. Standing behind him is official interperter Anthony Hervas (hair parted, wearing glasses and slightly stooped); against the wall behind Hervas is a bodyguard. Fidel Castro made the trip to Washington, D.C., in mid-April, 1959, in response to the invitation of Jules Dubois, editor of the Chicago Tribune and then president of the American Society of Newspaper Editors. Fidel remained in the United States for more than two weeks, eventually touring cities on the eastern seaboard such as Boston, Princeton, New Jersey and New York City. For other images of Fidel Castro's trip to Washington and New York, see Prints 56-78 and Contact Book V; for other images of Fidel Castro appearing on "Meet the Press," see Prints 56, 61, 63, and 65; for other images of Fidel Castro at the National Press Club, see Prints 60, 64, 67, 72, 75, and 76.
    - Contact Book V
      - Book V Prints 1-9: Fidel Castro trip to the United States
        - Book V Print 1: Fidel Castro at Cuban Embassy, 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 325)
          Documenting Fidel Castro's trip to the United States that began with a visit to Washington, D.C., in mid-April, this print shows Castro surrounded by a large crowd of curious Americans as he walks in the area around the Cuban Embassy at 2630 16th Street NW, where he was lodging. See also Prints 2, 4, 6 and 9.
        - Book V Print 2: Castro at Cuban Embassy, 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 326)
          Documenting Fidel Castro's trip to the United States that began with a visit to Washington, D.C. in mid-April, this print shows Castro surrounded by a large crowd of curious Americans as he walks in the area around the Cuban Embassy at 2630 16th Street NW, where he was lodging (visible in the background of frames 7 and 8). He is seen talking to a pair of small African-American boys and shaking hands through the windows of a passing bus. See also Prints 1, 4, 6 and 9.
        - Book V Print 3: Fidel Castro at Cuban Embassy, 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 327)
          Documenting Fidel Castro's trip to the United States that began with a visit to Washington, D.C. in mid-April, this print shows Castro surrounded by Cuban functionaries, bearded rebels and American reporters in the front vestibule and entrance of the Cuban Embassy, located at 2630 16th Street NW. See also Prints 1, 2, 4, 6, 7, 8, and 9.
        - Book V Print 4: Fidel Castro in Washington and New York City, 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 328)
          Documenting Fidel Castro's trip to the United States that began with a visit to Washington, D.C. in mid-April, the second, fourth, fifth and seventh rows of frames on this print show Castro surrounded by Cuban functionaries, bearded rebels and American reporters in the front vestibule of the Cuban Embassy, located at 2630 16th Street NW. The top, third and sixth rows of frames depict U.S. citizens carrying picket signs and protesting on the sidewalk in front of the Statler Hilton Hotel where Fidel Castro was speaking at a luncheon held by the American Society of Newspaper Editors. In a subsequent speech given in Central Park, New York City, Fidel claimed that the picketers were college students being paid $17 an hour for their time by pro-Batista groups seeking to discredit the Revolution as "communist." See also Prints 1, 2, 6, 7, 8 and 9.
        - Book V Print 5: Staff and government officials in Cuban Embassy, 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 329)
          Scenes of Cuban diplomatic staff and other government functionaries inside the Cuban Embassy located at 2630 Washington, D.C. during Fidel Castro's first visit to the United States after the triumph of revolutionary forces against Batista.
        - Book V Print 6: Fidel Castro at Cuban Embassy, 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 330)
          Documenting Fidel Castro's trip to the United States that began with a visit to Washington, D.C., in mid-April, this print shows Castro surrounded by a large crowd of curious Americans as he walks in the area around the Cuban Embassy at 2630 16th Street NW, where he was lodging, as well as impromptu meetings with reporters at the entrance to the embassy (frames 8-10, 11-15). Celia Sánchez appears in frames 6-7, standing inside the embassy before the interior balcony overlooking the central staircase. Frame 23 shows the Cuban flag flying over the roof of the embassy in the background as Fidel walks along with the accompanying crowd. See also Prints 1, 2, 4, 7 and 9.
        - Book V Print 7: Fidel Castro at Cuban Embassy, 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 331)
          Documenting Fidel Castro's trip to the United States that began with a visit to Washington, D.C., in mid-April, this print shows Castro surrounded by a large crowd of curious Americans as he walks in the area around the Cuban Embassy at 2630 16th Street NW, where he was lodging. See also Prints 1, 2, 4, 6 and 9.
        - Book V Print 8: Picketers during Fidel Castro's trip to the United States, 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 332)
          Taken during Fidel Castro's trip to the United States that began with a visit to Washington, D.C., in mid-April, this print shows U.S. citizens carrying picket signs and protesting on the sidewalk in front of the Statler Hilton Hotel where Fidel Castro was speaking at a luncheon held by the American Society of Newspaper Editors. In a subsequent speech given in Central Park, New York City, Fidel claimed that the picketers were American college students who were paid $17 an hour for their time by pro-Batista groups seeking to discredit the Revolution as "communist." Picket signs include the phrases "The commies are coming! They are with Fidel!"; "Fidel's beard hides a red face!"; "Castro says that anything that is wrong with Cuba is caused by the U.S."; "Fidelism. Revolutionism. Communism"; "Fidel-Newest dictator in western hemisphere"; "Castro says imperialistic U.S. a bad neighbor"; and "with friends like Fidel, the U.S. needs no enemies!" Frames 26 and 27 depict three police officers guarding the entrance to the ballroom in which Fidel is speaking. See also Prints 4 and 12.
        - Book V Print 9: Fidel Castro at Cuban Embassy, 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 333)
          Documenting Fidel Castro's trip to the United States that began with a visit to Washington, D.C., in mid-April, this print shows Castro surrounded by a large crowd of curious Americans as he walks in the area around the Cuban Embassy at 2630 16th Street NW, where he was lodging. Fidel is seen signing autographs, holding babies and talking jovially with members of the crowd. See also Prints 1, 2, 4 and 6.
      - Book V Print 10: Unidentified man; aftermath of night-time celebrations in Havana, 1959 February (Box 4, Folder 334)
        Top four rows of frames show part of the face of an unidentified balding man, probably an American, peering through the window of a door that appears to have no knob, but only a lock on the outside. It is possible that the man is a prisoner, although the grill on the door appears decorative and made of wood. Remaining frames show the aftermath of night-time street celebrations in Havana, possibly during Carnival of 1959. Frames 38-39 were taken from the corner of San Rafael Boulevard, looking northward on Prado. To the left of these frames is the terrace of the Hotel Inglaterra; the wooden frames used to separate seating for tourists and other on-lookers who would watch as carnival dancers and floats passed by.
      - Book V Prints 11-23: Fidel Castro trip to the United States
        - Book V Print 11: Fidel Castro awash in a human sea of officials, reporters and on-lookers on his visit to the United States in mid-April of 1959. Locations not clear, 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 335)
        - Book V Print 12: Picketers during Fidel Castro's trip to the United States; Fidel Castro in Washington, D.C., 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 336)
          Taken during Fidel Castro's trip to the United States that began with a visit to Washington, D.C., in mid-April, the first, fifth, and sixth rows of this print (as well as frame 22 of the bottom row) show U.S. citizens carrying picket signs and protesting on the sidewalk in front of the Statler Hilton Hotel where Fidel Castro was speaking at a luncheon held by the American Society of Newspaper Editors. In a subsequent speech given in Central Park, New York City, Fidel claimed that the picketers were American college students who were paid $17 an hour for their time by pro-Batista groups seeking to discredit the Revolution as "communist." Phrases used on the picket signs include: "Castro is the red Oppressor of Cuba!"; "Reds digging in U.S. back yard with help of Castro"; "Fidel Castro Red Puppet" and "We don't like beards. Barbers of America." Frame 36 shows three police men guarding the entrance to the ballroom where Fidel was speaking. The second row of frames and frames 8, 9, 10 of the third row show Fidel Castro surrounded by reporters, security and other embassy functionaries at the foot of the central staircase at the Cuban Embassy in Washington. Frames 11-17 and frames 18-21, 22 show Fidel Castro sitting and talking with President Eisenhower's recently appointed Secretary of State Christian A. Herter, who later hosted a lunch at his home for Fidel. See also Prints 4, 8, 15, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21 and 22.
        - Book V Print 13: Fidel Castro in New York City, 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 337)
          Images of Fidel Castro following his arrival at a hotel, probably the Statler Hitlon, in New York City during his April 1959 visit to the United States. In the top three rows of frames, Castro is seen talking on the phone. Frame 4 in the second-to-last row appears to depict Fidel and others' arrival at the hotel with the New York City skyline in the background. Frames 8-17 show the photographer's son sitting on Fidel Castro's lap.
        - Book V Print 14: Picketers during Fidel Castro trip to the United States, 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 338)
          Images of Americans carrying anti-Fidel picket signs and staging a protest in front of the building where Fidel Castro was delivering an address to the annual luncheon of the American Society of Newspaper Editors. Only a few signs are completely legible, such as ones reading "Communist Fidel Castro is ready to negotiate Cuba's sugar with Russia"; "Now Cuba is the Hungary of America"; and "We Israeli and Jews Anti-Communist protest for Castro's Red Operations." In all frames, city police are seen interspersed with the protestors. The reason for their presence may be the staging of a counter-protest in what appears to be the same area, on the other side of the street. See also Print 16.
        - Book V Print 15: Fidel Castro in New York City and Washington, D.C., 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 339)
          Top three rows of frames show Fidel Castro addressing the American Society of Newspaper Editors' annual meeting in Washington, D.C. Fidel originally made the trip, together with a large entourage of well over a hundred people, on April 14, 1959, in response to the invitation of Jules Dubois, editor of the Chicago Tribune and then president of the American Society of Newspaper Editors. Subsequent frames depict Fidel Castro at the reception held at the Cuban Embassy in Washington, D.C., for Cubans sent into exile by Batista's use of political terror against opponents. Much of the invited exile community had supported Castro's guerrillas financially from abroad. Frames 17-22 show a particularly warm and intimate encounter between Fidel and an unidentified blonde woman wearing a white feather hat. See also Prints 12, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21 and 22.
        - Book V Print 16: Fidel Castro visiting United States Capitol building and with Dominican exiles, 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 340)
          Top two rows of images show Fidel Castro visiting the U.S. Capitol building and frame 13 of the third row shows Castro entering a car marked "Department of State 1." Remaining images show a pro-Fidel demonstration in which participants appear to be Dominicans driven into exile by the political terror of the Rafael Trujillo dictatorship in the Dominican Republic. By the time of Fidel's visit, it was known that he publicly supported the training of guerrillas to topple the Trujillo regime, which had been hosting Fulgencio Batista and other high officials of the Batista dictatorship's intelligence divisions since the time of their escape from Cuba on January 1, 1959. Signs held by the picketers read "Nuestro lema Dios, Patria y Libertad"; "27 de Febrero Saluda a Fidel"; "1844 Independence 1959 Liberation"; "Democracy Yes Trujillo No"; "Cuban justice Batista style" (with accompanying image of anti-civilian violence); and "There's an iron curtain in Europe. A bamboo in China and a Sugar Cane Curtain in the Dominican Republic." See also Print 14.
        - Book V Print 17: Fidel Castro in Washington, D.C., 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 341)
          Fidel Castro addressing the American Society of Newspaper Editors' annual meeting in Washington, D.C. Fidel originally made the trip, together with a large entourage of well over a hundred people, on April 14, 1959, in response to the invitation of Jules Dubois, editor of the Chicago Tribune and then president of the American Society of Newspaper Editors. To Fidel Castro's immediate right in frames 3-15 and 21, 22-25, is Teresa Casuso, his special assistant and director of public relations before and after Fidel's visit to the United States; to her immediate right is Rufo López Fresquet, the revolutionary government's Minister of the Treasury until the fall of 1960. See also Prints 12, 15, 18, 19, 20, 21 and 22.
        - Book V Print 18: Fidel Castro in Washington, D.C., 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 342)
          Fidel Castro addressing the American Society of Newspaper Editors' annual meeting in Washington, D.C. Fidel originally made the trip, together with a large entourage of well over a hundred people, on April 14, 1959, in response to the invitation of Jules Dubois, editor of the Chicago Tribune and then president of the American Society of Newspaper Editors. To Fidel Castro's immediate right in frames 12-13 and then to his left in frames 15, 16, 17, is Teresa Casuso, his special assistant and director of public relations before and after Fidel's visit to the United States; to her immediate left in frames 21, 22-28, is Rufo López Fresquet, the revolutionary government's Minister of the Treasury until the fall of 1960. López Fresquet also appears in close-up, next to Fidel Castro in frame 17. These frames were taken as journalists approached the microphone to ask Fidel Castro a question. See also Prints 12, 15, 17, 19, 20, 21 and 22.
        - Book V Print 19: Fidel Castro in Washington, D.C., 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 343)
          Fidel Castro addressing the American Society of Newspaper Editors' annual meeting in Washington, D.C. Fidel originally made the trip, together with a large entourage of well over a hundred people, on April 14, 1959, in response to the invitation of Jules Dubois, editor of the Chicago Tribune and then president of the American Society of Newspaper Editors. To Fidel Castro's immediate left is Teresa Casuso, his special assistant and director of public relations before and after Fidel's visit to the United States; on Fidel's right is Rufo López Fresquet, the revolutionary government's Minister of the Treasury until the fall of 1960. López Fresquet also appears in close-up, next to Fidel Castro in frame 17. These frames were taken as journalists approached the microphone to ask Fidel Castro a question. See also Prints 12, 15, 17, 18, 20, 21 and 22.
        - Book V Print 20: Fidel Castro in Washington, D.C., 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 344)
          Top row of frames and frames 8-10 of the second row depict Fidel Castro's address to the American Society of Newspaper Editors' annual meeting in Washington, D.C. Fidel originally made the trip, together with a large entourage of well over a hundred people, on April 14, 1959, in response to the invitation of Jules Dubois, editor of the Chicago Tribune and then president of the American Society of Newspaper Editors. To Fidel Castro's immediate left in frame 3 is Teresa Casuso, his special assistant and director of public relations before and after Fidel's visit to the United States; on Fidel's right in the same frame is Rufo López Fresquet, the revolutionary government's Minister of the Treasury until the fall of 1960. Subsequent frames illustrate the reception held at the Cuban Embassy in Washington, D.C., for Cubans sent into exile by Batista's use of political terror against opponents. Much of the invited exile community had supported Castro's guerrillas financially from abroad. See also Prints 12, 15, 17, 18, 19, 21 and 22.
        - Book V Print 21: Fidel Castro in Washington, D.C., 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 345)
          Top two rows show Fidel Castro inside the Cuban Embassy in Washington, D.C., as he confers with other officials before heading downstairs to the entrance. Row three shows Fidel's visit to the U.S. Capitol building. Subsequent frames depict Fidel as he takes his seat at the head table alongside Rufo López Fresquet, the Cuban Minister of the Treasury, at the annual luncheon of the American Society of Newspaper Editors, held at the Statler Hilton. The final three frames of the print show a policeman standing next to a group of anti-Castro protesting picketers outside the hotel entrance. See also Prints 12, 15, 17, 18, 19 and 20.
        - Book V Print 22: Fidel Castro in Washington, D.C., 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 346)
          These images depict Fidel Castro's address to the American Society of Newspaper Editors' annual meeting in Washington, D.C. Fidel originally made the trip, together with a large entourage of well over a hundred people, on April 14, 1959, in response to the invitation of Jules Dubois, editor of the Chicago Tribune and then president of the American Society of Newspaper Editors. To Fidel Castro's immediate right, Rufo López Fresquet, the revolutionary government's Minister of the Treasury until the fall of 1960; sitting next to the latter is Teresa Casuso, special assistant to Fidel and director of public relations before and after Fidel's visit to the United States. See also Prints 12, 15, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21 and 22.
        - Book V Print 23: Fidel Castro in Washington, D.C., 1959 April (Box 4, Folder 347)
          Top three rows of frames capture Fidel Castro's address to the American Society of Newspaper Editors' annual meeting in Washington, D.C. Fidel originally made the trip, together with a large entourage of well over a hundred people, on April 14, 1959, in response to the invitation of Jules Dubois, editor of the Chicago Tribune and then president of the American Society of Newspaper Editors. The fourth and fifth rows of frames show Fidel and a group of bearded rebel officers as they visit the buildings near the U.S. Capitol. Frames 5 and 6 show two unidentified, elegantly dressed Cuban women in close-up as they apparently attempt to get past a security guard inside an office. Final row of frames show a policeman standing next to a group of anti-Castro protesting picketers outside the hotel entrance. See also Prints 12, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21 and 22.
      - Book V Prints 24-29: Fidel Castro arriving in Havana (May 17, 1959) after trip to United States
        - Book V Print 24: Crowds at Fidel Castro's return from trip to the United States, 1959 May (Box 4, Folder 348)
          Images of the multitudes gathered at Havana's international airport on May 17, 1959 to receive Fidel Castro upon his return from the highly successful, four-week visit to the United States and Argentina. Riding on the jeep in frames 36 and 37 is Camilo Cienfuegos. In the center of frames 16 and 17 stand Fidel Castro with Raúl Castro at his back as they wade through a crowd after exiting the plane. Also visible in frames 4-7 is Fidel Castro greeting the crowds. See also Prints 25, 26, 27, 28 and 29.
        - Book V Print 25: Crowds at Fidel Castro's return from trip to the United States and Castro addressing crowds, 1959 May (Box 4, Folder 349)
          Frame 13 of the top row shows Andrew St. George sitting on the ground with a press band on his left forearm accompanied by an unidentified Cuban. They appear to be awaiting the arrival of Fidel at the airport following his highly successful, four-week visit to the United States and Argentina. Images in frames 9-12 show helmeted members of a national police force as they wait to receive Fidel Castro; frames 4-6 show Fidel Castro descending from the plane at a distance with men bearing the flag of the "Policía Nacional Revolucionaria" amidst the large crowd gathered on the tarmac. The bottom frames provide close-up shots of an unidentified light-eyed guerrilla sporting a particularly impressive beard as well as a close-up of Fidel Castro and other officials waving triumphantly from the podium in front of the monument to José Martí in what was then called the Plaza Cívica in Havana. This image documents Fidel's address to the nation given almost immediately upon his return to Cuba from the United States and Argentina. See also Prints 24, 26, 27, 28 and 29.
        - Book V Print 26: Security forces waiting for Fidel Castro's return from trip to the United States, 1959 May (Box 4, Folder 350)
          Images of various unidentified barbudos and security forces assembled to greet Fidel Castro upon his triumphant return from a highly successful four-week visit to the United States (May 17, 1959). Efigenio Ameijeiras stands in full dress uniform as Captain of the National Revolutionary Police at the center of frame 8. Behind Ameijeiras, it is clear that the balcony of the airport's terminal has been decorated with signs reading "Bienvenido FIDEL." Row 6 of the print features close-up images of Fidel and Camilo Cienfuegos smiling and waving to crowds gathered to hear Fidel's report to the nation on his visit to the United States at the foot of the monument to José Martí in Havana's Plaza Cívica. See also Prints 24, 25, 27, 28, and 29.
        - Book V Print 27: Crowds waiting for return of Fidel Castro from trip to the United States, 1959 May (Box 4, Folder 351)
          This print documents the spectacle of civilian supporters, officials and military authorities from all divisions of Cuba's armed forces, including the navy and national police, that assembled to greet Fidel Castro and his entourage upon their return from a highly successful, four-week visit to the United States and Argentina. Frame 13 shows Fidel Castro emerging from the plane and subsequent rows depict him as he descends the stairs of the plane and begins to encounter the massive crowd. See also Prints 24, 25, 26, 28 and 29.
        - Book V Print 28: Crowds waiting for return of Fidel Castro from trip to the United States, 1959 May (Box 4, Folder 352)
          Scenes of the gathering of a massive crowd in Havana's Plaza Cívica to hear Fidel Castro address the nation upon his return from a highly successful four-week trip to the United States and Argentina. See also Prints 24, 25, 26, 27 and 29.
        - Book V Print 29: Crowds waiting for return of Fidel Castro from trip to the United States, 1959 May (Box 4, Folder 353)